wisdom and where does wisdom
fit into this whole program that you're
talking about there's definitely now
sacredness and spirituality there's
aspiration there's transformation
you know there's people have to have to
have the you know they have to have the
right insight they have to discern
use this as a tool not crawl into the
hole but
like more explicitly now more focally
how does wisdom fit into this for you
i suppose the first response after that
is i'm a i'm 38 and i jump uh
between trees right like
wisdom is such an interesting word i
like i've been insightful
for most of my life i guess
my mom tells stories about like going on
walks with me and like
finding me discussing the nature of god
with people when i was four years old
yeah yeah yeah yeah
that's clear and so at 16 years
so um i actually the first religion that
i got involved in the the only religion
i've really been involved in was a um
was a native american sort of uh
uh recovery i don't i don't know
describe it right uh there's a bunch of
uh of white people following this native
american leader johnny moses
um doing something called sewus um
so i was in this community and and i was
talking about my ideas whatever those
ideas were at the time and a lot of
people would tell me that i was wise
right and and it just stuck in my craw
because
how could a 16 year old be wise i had no
experience for me
wisdom was was experience married
to insight yeah yeah at the time
um i i love the way that you've
articulated wisdom
um i don't know that i mean
i don't know that that i've art that
i've have i
integrated into the way that i'm
thinking about what i'm doing i want i
want to afford people
inside generation which is very deeply
connected to that and
i think i mean there's this idea
one of the things that i ask is do
people do the right
it's the meechan question right um most
of morality is just cowardice
yeah right i feel like we
we we've lived through the easiest times
in human history
and maybe that's ending yeah yeah yeah
but but people most people behave
well in these nice times
not because they have a well-cultivated
virtue and wisdom
and and ethics but because the game is
set up so
that's what's rewarded to some degree
yeah yeah yeah
and and i think that if you can set the
game up to reward good behavior that's
great
but you want to build also the people
such that even when the game
shifts when things change that's still
what's rewarded
and i have this
or at least rewarding i don't see wisdom
right i don't i don't see our political
class as wise i don't see
our academic class as wise and i also
see
i mean i'm getting a little passion here
but i see cowardice everywhere
i see people who who who have
who are not willing to look deeply at
themselves who are not willing to try
hard things who are not willing to
to take on difficult questions who who
who are not guys that i'd want beside me
in a shield wall
right right right right and i think it's
because
because they haven't had the chance to
test themselves and to grow themselves
and because are because there has to be
something
you know more there has to be something
we're aspiring to and there has to be
systems that
give us that opportunity for serious
play but also a necessity for discipline
right um and that that that's that's
ultimately what i'm interested in is
that that
that that cultivation of virtue through
practice and
and one of those is is wisdom but i
would say that in the
in the ecology of of
of of the cultivation of virtue
my role and what my work has been about
is more about courage and your role is
more about wisdom
um that's fair that's fair but i
i i want and i'm very attracted to the
idea of the synthesis
but i think that if i'm uh at least at
this stage of my life
right if i'm going to to lead people on
a path i feel like
the path around courage is the path that
i'm most
most um most informed with
right most resonant with yeah i
i i feel i have a a subject matter
expertise that i can fairly put myself
in front of people there
and if people get wisdom from what i'm
doing and perhaps they do
then that's great but to take on wisdom
as
at the center of it feels presumptuous
yeah yeah fair enough well i mean we're
all
we are always and only supposed to be
lovers
and the whole point about the metaphor
we can't
we can't win by playing the game that's
right
my way of trying to understand what it
is to not play their game
and to shift over to in a totally
different game to shift the culture